Shiquan Zhang

Shenzhen, China | (86)139-2840-7251 | zhangshiquan19@mails.ucas.ac.cn | https://github.com/sqzhang-jeremy

PERSONAL STATEMENT

I am a self-discipline and self-learning student and I love to try something new. I was engaged in the research of computer vision, machine learning and medical imaging. I am passionate about the application of artificial intelligence in biomedical field and dedicated to make contributions in healthcare.

EDUCATION

University of Chinese Academy of Science (UCAS)	Beijing, China
Shenzhen Institute of Advanced Technology (SIAT)	Shenzhen, China
M.Eng. in Computer Technology GPA: 3.78/4.0	Jun. 2019 – Jun.2022
The first place in professional interview in Postgraduate Entrance Examination	2019
Hainan University (HNU)	Haikou, China
B.Eng. in Mechatronic Engineering GPA: 3.27/4.0 Ranking: 20/111	Sep. 2015 – Jun. 2019
HNU Outstanding Graduate	2019
HNU Elite Youth Training Program (3%)	Mar. 2017 – Jun. 2019

RESEARCH EXPERIENCES

• Domain Distributions' Removal in Radiomic Features, Independent

May. 2021 – Present

SIAT-Medical AI Center, advisor: P.I. Zhicheng Li

• Discrepancy across domain distributions (e.g., multicenter, scanner model, reconstruction settings) may greatly influence radiomic features extraction and cause degradation in the analysis performance. We have carried out some experiments trying to improve the Combat algorithm in feature domain.

• Patent Foramen Ovale (heart disease) Classification, Independent

Sep. 2019 - Apr. 2021

SIAT-Paul C. Lauterbur Biomedical Imaging Lab & Shenzhen University & Peking Tiantan Hospital, advisor: P.I. Yang Xiao and Prof. Yongjin Zhou

- Preliminarily achieved an efficient automated diagnosis to make patent foramen ovale binary-classification in 2D contrast echocardiography videos, which firstly explored the feasibility of PFO diagnosis with artificial intelligence and achieved 0.7847 sensitivity, 0.7500 specificity and 0.8063 AUC compared to clinicians' 0.5388, 0.8318 and x.
- Utilized CNNs (Deeplabv3+/Unet) to make 2D left atrium segmentation.
- Proposed a time-domain preprocessing method to remove inherent interference (noise and motion artefacts) in echocardiography, which projects minimal gray interval from TTE videos to cTTE videos, thereby minimizing inherent interference as much as possible.
- Developed a two-stage detection method, a superpixel segmentation method and a radiomics method, in space-domain, which coarsely aggregates the features of similar pixels into superpixel block and discriminate bubbles under the constraints of grayscale threshold and elliptic or circular circularity, and further finely makes radiomics feature extraction and selection.

• Muscle Atrophy Disease Classification, Participate

Sep. 2020 – Apr. 2021

SIAT-Paul C. Lauterbur Biomedical Imaging Lab, advisor: P.I. Yang Xiao

• Utilized 3D-ResNet to make binary classification in 2D shear-wave elastography videos, which realized the effective discrimination of muscle atrophy and achieved 86.89% accuracy and 88.89% F1-Score.

• Other Projects Experiences

• Huawei Cloud Cup Precipitation Nowcasting

May. - Jun. 2020

Enhanced the performance of convGRU through introducing GAN module to make prediction of future precipitation in radar data.

User Cellphone Traffic Upgrade Prediction
 Preprocessed and analyzed text data, practiced feature engineering, utilized basic machine learning models to make traffic upgrade classification.

Quantitative Analysis of Contrast-Enhanced Ultrasound of Osteonecrosis of Femoral Head
Jun. - Aug. 2019
Preprocessed ultrasound videos, utilized VGG16 to make segmentation and extracted features of ROIs to plot Time-Intensity Curve to analyze curve parameters.

Sliding Double-deck Parking Space

2017. Sep - Jan. 2018

Designed a sliding mechanical transmission control system in car parking area, which can semi-automatically park, lift and rotate, and participated in the physical production, test and calibration. #Video link

 positioning, sensor detection, solar battery and false alarm release modules.

PUBLICATIONS AND PATENTS

- [1] Yang, J., Zhang, H., Wang, Y., **Zhang, S.**, et al. The Efficacy of Contrast Transthoracic Echocardiography and Contrast Transcranial Doppler for the Detection of Patent Foramen Ovale Related to Cryptogenic Stroke. BioMed research international, 2020. # https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/1513409
- [2] Yin, L., Du, L., Li, Y., Xiao, Y., **Zhang, S.**, et al. Quantitative Evaluation of Gastrocnemius Medialis Stiffness During Passive Stretching Using Shear Wave Elastography in Patients with Parkinson's Disease: A Prospective Preliminary Study. Korean Journal of Radiology, 2021. # https://doi.org/10.3348/kjr.2020.1338
- [3] Zhang, X., Xiao, Y., Wang, C., **Zhang, S.**, et al. Deep residual convolutional neural network for the diagnosis of muscle atrophy based on dynamic ultrasound shear-wave elastography video. Chinese Journal of Biomedical Engineering, 2021. (minor revision) [4] A coauthor paper (under review)
- [5] **Zhang, S.**, et al. Method and system for diagnosing patent foramen oval, CN Invention and PCT, CN202011373095.3& PCT/CN2020/139680, First trial.
- [6] Zhang, X., Xiao, Y., **Zhang, S.**, et al. Deep residual convolutional neural network for the diagnosis of muscle atrophy based on dynamic ultrasound shear-wave elastography video, CN Invention and PCT, CN202011230395.6 & PCT/CN2020/139413, First trial. [7] Tang, Z., Zhang, J., **Zhang, S.**, et al. A new mechanical impact buffering device for automobile, CN Utility Model, ZL201721292832.0, Issued.

Selected Awards

National inspirational scholarship	2017
HNU merit student and excellent student leader	2016, 2017
HNU second-class scholarship	2016
Chinese Academy of Sciences Public Science Day's outstanding volunteer	2021
National top 100 summer social practice team and outstanding individual	2018
Haikou International Marathon Competition's outstanding volunteer	2017

LEARNING EXPERIENCES

- Convolutional Neural Networks for Visual Recognition (CS231n), Standford University, Online
- Statistical Data Analysis, Johns Hopkins University, Coursera #Code and certificate on github
- Artificial Intelligence in Healthcare (CS271), Standford University, Online

SKILLS

Standardized tests: IELTS 6 (R6.5 L6.5 S5.5 W6) in Jul. 2021

Programming skills:

Proficient in Python, R, Matlab and C

Experiences with LaTex, Javascript and HTML

Technical Linux, Pytorch, Tensorflow and Keras

Software skills:

Proficient in AutoCAD, Pro/E, Adobe Photoshop, Premiere, Illustrator and AfterEffects

Language: Chinese (native), English **Extracurriculum**: #More details

Last Updated: 210906.